[Music]
all right hello and welcome everyone to
actinflab live stream number 38.1
it's february
16th 2022
welcome to the actin flap we are a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live stream
just release an unending torrent of
emojis if you have to speak or just
raise your hand i'm sure that we'll get
to it
if you're watching live please feel free
to write questions in the live chat and
we'll have enough time to hang out and
discuss
during this dot one where we'll be
opening into the paper
check out activeinference.org
for updated information on participating
in any of the labs activities
i hope you'll find something that
resonates with you
today in actinf
livestream number 38.1 we're going to be
learning and discussing this cool paper
the evolution of brain architectures for
predictive coding and active inference
by pazulo parr and fristen from
december 2021
and
we're just going to enjoy discussing it
and opening up any ideas or questions
that us here on the panel have or those
who are live chatting us
and we have some ideas and thoughts
prepared a few things that we know that
we can go into and also i hope that
everyone has
brought some other prepared seeds and
also of course
spontaneously
feeling like new things are arising
so we'll just start with some
introduction and warm-up we can each say
hi and then maybe it'd be cool to just
also mention like what
got you excited about the paper or what
made you want to discuss this paper
what's something that stayed
with you
so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and
i was very excited by the evolutionary
focus
a lot of my
research over the last years has been in
evolution in ecology so it's always
awesome to see how people are thinking
about how active inference free energy
principle and evolutionary studies can
all be learning from one another and
i'll pass to stephen
hello i'm stephen silly i'm in toronto
um i'm really interested in how this
paper connects to my work with
spatial meaning making and social
topographies
because this paper talks about
a more biological
nascent
stage of development rather than some
higher order meaning
often people think about and i'm really
interested in how this sort of grounded
bottom up
inactive ecological approaches can be
thought about as something where we can
actually
ground a lot of our meaning making and
so i'm interested in how this
might match with some of that thinking
and i will pass this over to dean
thanks steven i'm dean i'm in calgary uh
what i found interesting about the paper
is that
given that i've worked with a lot of
young learners for a lot of my life
i
was really it was really interesting to
see
how
this
affirmed a lot of the thinking that i
was doing when i was trying to get
people past the idea that science is
only about the biology and the chemistry
and the physics that there is a
statistical and predictive component to
this and those relationships in that in
that realm um can build certain sense of
what the
underlying architecture is so as i said
this is this is a lot of this is
affirmations and it's kind of it's it's
kind of seen as being
not part of what is typically addressed
as core learning but i think it should
be back to you dan
cool nice intro let's just start with a
big question
and then
either of you have any reflections on
the big question
or we'll go over to blank slide and just
bring up some
questions we have
and also it might be good to go over
just some of the key points in the paper
like what did they actually do in terms
of their contribution
so the big question or at least one way
to phrase something that might bring
someone to approach this paper
what is the evolutionary
neurophysiological basis of cognition
and how do complex cognitive phenotypes
arise like you don't go from zero to
colony in one time step
how does it happen that evolution arises
from precursor
sometimes simpler but also sometimes
more complicated
precursors
steven mentioned like what is the basis
for sense making and cognition and sense
making are very related
and what's been fun over these
last weeks
and months is we've explored
basic
or simple or reduced or basal cognition
from a variety of perspectives like we
talked about the bioelectric components
of
thinking about basal cognition with mike
levin now we're thinking about a
slightly different
approach to understanding basal
cognition which we'll be discussing here
and then also we've looked at some of
these more complex cognitive phenotypes
like
mental action counterfactuals
deep
temporal inference
all the abductive
logic which we'll get into probably
later
um
how can we use integrative models of
perception cognition action and impact
like active inference
to study this whole continuum and
diversity of relatively simpler
in our perspective cognition and also
relatively more complex
cognitive phenotypes
and everything in between so yes stephen
and then on with it
thanks daniel yeah i mean i suppose also
what what some of the paradigm
impacts of that of taking that
all the way through um and one question
that might come up which you may or may
not have an answer to or thoughts on but
um you know mike
levin's work with the
tediological cones
at the different nested levels and how
this sort of
could be thinking about what kind of
um action
control potential
you know in in these different nested
levels might exist
um i would be interested to think about
how this may um
either be able to connect to that i can
see it connecting philosophically or
whether there's another bridge needed
between this modeling and that type of
modelling so just something i'll mention
great
um
dean anything to add or perhaps i'm
gonna wait till you get to uh figure one
okay
so
we won't go through
all of the
binary points in the paper that's
for the reading of the paper itself nor
will we even go over all of the overview
which is what the dot zero video 38.0 is
for so you know turn back time and watch
that one if you haven't or pause the
video if you're not watching it live
but
what this paper does
as evidenced by their roadmap
is
introduce a few basic principles of
cognition
predictive regulation and control
and then also
structure learning in generative models
that's not how every neurophysiology
text is going to begin
the building blocks of cognition it's
not how every evolutionary
neurophysiology text is going to be
framing cognition but that's what they
do here and that will play into how it's
similar and different than other
approaches
then with those building blocks in hand
or on the floor
they provide three examples of motifs
that ancestral brains
may
be modeled as having or may have
actually had
with those three examples in hand
it's then possible for them to state
a more general way of thinking about the
transitions amongst different structures
these structures represent
brain design as structure learning in
generative models
that is called an evolutionary algebra
and they introduce
five operators that can basically either
leave unchanged or
change
the structure
of brain design
with respect to generative models
and each of those are explored in terms
of what are the architectural changes
that that evolutionary transition
is
and then what are the functional
consequences of that kind of an
evolutionary transition
then they have some discussions about
how
sequences or patterns of application of
this evolutionary algebra could lead to
different evolutionary phenomena so
for example increasing temporal depth in
the future means that models are
increasingly prospective
increasing temporal depth in the past is
like memory etc
and then they close with
mapping to a phylogenetic tree and
thinking about
that evolutionary algebra of state
transitions being mapped onto the
bifurcating tree structure that's called
the phylogenetic tree which shows the
relatedness of different
life forms
um
that's the roadmap
let's go to the long-awaited figure one
and talk about the action perception
cycle and predictive regulation and so
they're again discussing this in the
context of predictive regulation
anticipatory regulation cybernetics
and control
as a basic design principle for the
brain
so dean what do you see here or what
would be cool to think about
so what did this follows i think is is
the usual pattern when we're trying to
uh
explain where we're going to go
and so you just had a road map up and i
think a road map is a way
for the people who are reading the road
map to find their way what i think what
this diagram
shows is that in that in the middle of
there there's something called a
discrepancy
and that discrepancy is later going to
be given up given a label y
um and
what i think is really interesting here
is there's a there's a flip potentially
that can happen here that discrepancy is
where what i would describe as a rule
factory
and rule in the sense that we find
patterns
that's kind of our place where where as
it says the prediction and the
observation come together and i believe
that that's different than a road map
which is find your way i believe that
that discrepancy of that rule factory is
way binding and i think
what we have the potential to do with
this paper
because of the way that they
have sort of presented the information
is
the words
become x
eventually become
explicated rules which then become
action in the phenomenological space
that's where it gets really really
interesting because i think most of the
time when people look at things as a
subject they've taken the world
and they've collapsed down to words and
diagrams and models what this
potentially allows us to do is flip that
and move from the words back out into
the
space
with a little bit more confidence so
yeah that's why i wanted to kind of
start here
because i think the word discrepancy
it's the first time i've seen it in this
kind of figure
model and i really like it
cool
yeah it makes me think about uh
setting off on the road trip on the
mental actions that
reflect
the paper
and there's the road map which is super
informative but it is like
instructionalism it's saying you're
going to go two streets and then take a
left turn at the stop sign and then when
this happens then you'll do that and if
you've seen this then you've gone too
far kind of classic instruction
type
sequences
here we have a figuring out because it's
visually arranged with some local
connectivity that's suggestive of a
causal connection through time but
by no means is there only one way to
read this simultaneous figure
and
so that allows
potentially for more of a figuring out
including the figuring out of rules
yes it is indeed a little different with
discrepancy at the intersection here
stephen
yeah so this ties in with
the lower bound evidence
um
control approach on of action so you
know the idea is that
action is what we can
tractably approximate
um
and
perception is
uh something that we can access but
can't
and we can try to make more sense of but
is is is a harder
a harder uh
piece of the equation to get together to
get a handle on so um i'm wondering if
that's
i mean how do you feel about that
decoration in terms of
its its use across
other areas of applied active inference
so i think it's a
it could make things a little bit more
digestible for a number of contexts
okay i'm
thinking about this in the context of
recognizing that it's different than
other action perception loops that we've
seen which is just really important to
keep in mind that we're not
perceiving something that we're
projecting too much
because
other times the outgoing arrow from the
entity is what
if this were a markov blanket type
diagram which they often are
the outgoing arrow would reflect active
states and then the statistical
dependencies that are outgoing
but where is action
it's on the bottom right
so
let's really try to understand why the
pieces are placed this way
the outgoing feature of the cognitive
entity is the prediction
and here's observation coming in if this
were a markov blanket diagram we'd have
the world
and then the incoming statistical arrow
would be the observation that would be
the sensory states
so
here
it's the outgoing prediction of the
entity and the incoming sensory data or
observation
those two are being
differentiated
to form a discrepancy
which is just a qualitative term but it
could be
then brought a little bit more formally
into a prediction error
or
a little bit even beyond that into like
a free energy differential
this
discrepancy
has two arrows coming out of it
from the discrepancy
is
a rising perception
and the changing of beliefs
does perception always involve changing
beliefs
and the discrepancy is also giving rise
to action
so what kind of a thing is discrepancy
such that the inputs are prediction and
observation
and the outputs are perception and
action
so at the very least this is not the
bayesian graph representations that
we've seen before
or that we'll see
in just a few slides with a more
traditional interpretation of nodes as
random variables and edges as
statistical dependencies
this is a little bit more like a thought
map
that then connects to
the variational free energy equation
which we talked about in number 37 a lot
more but just
to recall there's the red and the blue
lines
these two different components
of the variational free energy and those
are shown again here so check out 37 to
learn more about the red and the blue
and about
variational and expected free energy but
for here
we're starting with this
action prediction discrepancy
motif
and then connecting it
to perception and action as variational
free energy minimization stephen
i think one thing that's useful with
this
more nascent
representation is this discrepancy
can go in different
different directions so it can be
discrepancy in terms of temporal
occurrence
when was the prediction predicted to
happen
when was it observed but it could also
be what kind of prediction
and what kind of observation or
whereabouts was the prediction
whereabouts was the observation there's
many different
um and at different scales you know so
there may be
that um
at the kind of lower levels there's
quite a big jump between
when i predict
the baseball coming to my hand
when that prediction was made when that
observation occurs
and also when that is
chained up at different
slower bigger steps of the
um nested markov
blanket sort of sequence so you this
idea of discrepancy is uh
i suppose is probably the biggest bucket
they could find i would imagine at that
at that spot and that may be partly why
it's there
can i just add to that stephen i think
one of the things that's interesting is
especially after just doing the 37 paper
where we were talking about guides
to me
the timing of this was absolutely
immaculate because now all of a sudden
we've gone from guiding to almost taking
potentially a referee's position
on the world
which is a whole different thing than
than taking the taking up the position
of being a guide
and that was i mean that that's not
nuance that's not subtle
that's quite quite an identity shift and
we're going to actually get into
identity when we look at some of the
evolutionary steps later on but i i
wanted to slow down on this because i
thought
this that's not that's not a minor
change
that's a whole different perspective
shift and i think we need to really make
note of that because i think it colors
a lot of what's to follow
what makes you say that we're a referee
in this situation
discrepancy
there's a difference between what what
the world is telling us and then how we
rule on them
so think of any game where you get into
an argument with the refs
are they wrong are you wrong it doesn't
really matter the point is that there's
a difference
that's when you said differential
graphing is maybe one of the ways to be
able to make that explicit
but that's not how it's typically
framed out
when we're talking about bayesian or
markovian stuff
so i think this is i think this is a big
move
i know it might seem like a tiny one but
i think as we go again as we go deeper
into this paper it affirms a lot of the
stuff that i actually saw when you're
trying to go out there
and forage
and figure
so
i'm excited to keep going
yeah it could be like the observation
the the baseball player is running
towards the base
and the coach is observing and there's
this ongoing prediction and observation
with no discrepancy because part of the
generative model includes the person
moving through time
and then
given the observation and the generative
model
the coach predicts slash expects and
prefers which will
come to you again later with the three
piece
um that the baseball player is safe you
rarely see um
super animated refusals when a call has
gone towards somebody but it's when it
has gone against it's violated their
fitness that there's a discrepancy
with what the referee has called and
what the interested coach has called
and that is going to lead to
some consequences and again we're still
not at the bayesian graph
level but that's going to be the next
figure stephen
this can then
build on
the idea of what's cognitive what what
can you have a perspective on so i think
what you're saying there with this
referee position is
as well as the kind of
the swarming dynamics and the kind of
inactive processes much of which is
beyond our
ability to sense or
integrate
what is it once it starts to hit what's
the big bucket at the kind of cognition
level that still isn't
too much of a
a um an inflation
so in this case here discrepancy there
is a sense of being able to distinguish
perception and action at some level and
find a discrepancy which in some
ways i would imagine covers a lot of
what cognition would require to be
thought of in a cognition way
other types of action for instance how
we heal
or grow
maybe um action and perception won't be
so separated but this is trying to come
up the idea of cognition so maybe that
also informs this process
cool so section two again was just about
the two concepts of
predictive regulation and control that's
what we saw here
predictive
and control
so it's just conceptually laid out
in figure 2
they formalize brain design
as structured learning in generative
models
so here we have a different figure
we still have
the
cognitive entity
and the world
we add in
one layer of
absolutely essential active terms which
is generative model
generative process
the generative model is the cognitive
entities model of
the generative process
is the underlying phenomena that gives
rise to observations
it's the difference between the
cognitive model of vision a generative
model of vision
and the generative process of visual
input which is like
photons and the sun and all of that so
these are very different they're
complementary
but just so that we're really clear
going forward that we're going to be
using those in their specific sense not
using them like oh well it's a
generative model because this is a model
of cognition that makes me excited and
think of ideas that's not how we're
using generative model here so just to
be clear on that
now
we see
action
as changing the world represented by you
and the cognition involves partially
action selection
policy selection
planning as inference
but
not going to all those details yet
which can have some influence on
actual unobserved hidden states the
world x star
x
is the cognitive model
of that hidden state of the world that
is
being inferred
and y
is the observation that then feeds back
into the cognitive model
so that's what these
nodes mean
it's about
partitioning
the cognitive model
from the generative process
separating the generative model from the
generative process
and we're starting to see
the traditional blanket form with
observations having incoming statistical
dependencies
and actions having outgoing statistical
what else do either of you see in this
model
yatine
hey let's see
so
let's go back to being a referee for a
second
the assumption is that you're already
attending
and most of these models that that we
have
taken up in the past
especially in 37
what they try to focus on is
getting from a to b
what this is essentially saying is
let's add something to that translation
right from a to b
whatever we're trying to incorporate in
this representation let's maybe look at
the interpretation part of it now and
the recitation part of it so if i'm the
umpire and we can all be umpires we
don't have to do that just in a baseball
game
this is incorporating now a certain
critical process
i was attending and i saw this but then
there were 60 000 other people also
paying attention
and they saw that
that's where i think it this is getting
really interesting now this is actually
bringing it back to sort of i still
think it's an instrumental piece but i
think now we're going to incorporate
some of the reality and is where the
sixty thousand wrong
or is the one person who yelled out
safe
wrong
that's what i see in this because that
you is is definitely embedded in
the generative process
not the generative model
okay thanks dean stephen
so the
question that comes into mind is where
the body is in all of this
and i sense that
the generative processes the bigger
process with the world the generative
model
um gives a way to access those
priors and and to give away the hidden
states
and the cognitive model
generally speaking cognition is thought
of more in terms of deductive and
inductive
reasoning and logic
and and it could be that the
that there's elements of the abductive
that could be held within
the kind of body and i suppose there's a
question there
um that
to how and where that is i don't think
anyone quite knows the answer to that
but uh
um that's that's my thought
so let's
remember that this
partitioning
is specific to a given instantiation of
model-based science
just like majeed was talking about
so we're not going around and assigning
aspects or phenomena of the world into
either generative model or generative
process so where does the body fit in
well
with respect to a model
of the body being a structurally real
thing that gives rise to
observations it's a generative process
looking at the coin from the other side
and thinking of the body
as a generative model of its niche
doing inference on certain things or
acting as if in that sense it's
generative model so
different kinds of entities are not
going to be just assigned simply to one
side or the other
it's going to come down to what is
specifically being discussed
there's a few other um
not complexifiers but first off just
note that the no the notation here is
not the same that's used elsewhere
so we will move towards better and
cleaner or reformatable notation but
like x star
as a external state and x as an internal
state
might be clearer for some people
it also carries a little bit of a
baggage that the hidden state is exactly
what is being inferred about the
external world
like there's a temperature parameter in
the brain and then there's a temperature
parameter outside in the world
as we explore in the representations
paper
it doesn't necessarily have to be that
way there could be
in a hidden state internally having to
do with movement left or right
and then there's a temperature variable
outside
and then the model
the generative model of the cognizer is
about movement conditioned on
temperature observations but not
necessarily
simply a thermometer being
instantiated in the head so
it's like
good to look at this graphically and
think about what is being connected to
what without
worrying
too much about all of these
side questions but
this is what they're setting up as the
basis of their further discussion
which is it's about prediction and
control
and we can use bayesian graphical
approaches to represent that stephen
and that inferred state as you mentioned
it's uh in some ways that's always
slightly hidden from us like how is that
what is that mean to be an inferred
state
in terms of is that the cognition
that's coming out of that in some sort
of deductive
or can it be an effective
sense of how well something's going so
again it's not
directly asked here
but
accessing that is one of the big
problems that happens is how do you
access
what has been inferred
when it's not necessarily something you
can access through
sort of direct reporting from a
subject matter or from a from
participant
right like another example of that might
be somebody who has skilled action with
respect to investing
but they may not be able to give an
estimate for a number that's a certain
you know asset is expected to be at
because it's not like they're doing the
asset price prediction and then doing a
strategy the cognitive model may have a
very different structure
so
we explored it in the representations
paper but like there would be ways in
which therefore that investment decision
is not a representation
of the actual stock market
because it's not the same variable
but then the aboutness of the investment
decision would be
a representation with respect to what
was happening in the generative process
so those were some of the like
side avenues that we've looked at
previously but they're all in play at
once
and so the question is just how to
linearly structure
to respect the specific contributions
that are made here
and the insight that can be gleaned
without um
every single time
pulling back to some of these questions
but it's great that we have like
specific papers and memes and core terms
that we can
refer to
and then
carry on with what they actually
contribute
okay any thoughts on one or two before
we get into the
structure of the um
aloe stat
or the homeostat first i guess
let's go
okay again so
we're going to go from this black and
white you know
dorothy still in kansas
mode
to
some predictive motifs of ancestral
brains
and the three motifs the red green and
blue
are
homeostasis
so returning to a set point allostasis
anticipating or approaching a set point
in the future which could be a fixed or
changing one
and then implementing behavioral control
not just
scalar homeostasis or allostasis on an
enteroceptive variable
okay
citation 20 in the paper chance at all
from the future march 22
is where to look for more details on the
homeostatic formulation that they're
using here
but we can see it in terms of their
figure three
okay so the left side just for reference
there's figure two
so that we can remember the structure of
perception cognition action impact that
the authors are working with here
and we're gonna connect this black and
white figure 2
to
figure 3a
this is a graphical model
graphical in both senses meaning visual
like we're perceiving it through
computer graphics and graphical meaning
like a network so nodes and edges
because there's computer graphics that
aren't
network topologies
but this happens to be a computer
graphic that we're perceiving visually
that also is reflecting a graph in terms
of nodes and connected edges
it's a generative model
for
the regulation of a single interceptive
variable so here's a and b with the
homeostat and c we split out to talk
about later but first a and b
this generative model includes an
enteroceptive thermoreceptor
and a belief about body temperature
the prior over x
which is body temperature is kept fixed
and hence it acts as a cybernetic set
point
any discrepancy between the predictive
thermoreceptor activity given beliefs
about x so y conditioned on x
and the measured y is registered as a
prediction error that is canceled out by
an autonomic response u for example a
thermoregulatory response so
hidden state
on temperature beliefs about temperature
y
the thermometer
perception
and then
there's the selection of action so some
sort of like vasodilation or
thermoregulatory response
and then that's going to change the
underlying unobserved true temperature
but that's not um
needing to be shown so any comments on
that first part we're looking just at
the top half of 3a
and connecting x y
to um
you action
can you still hear me because i yeah
can you take can you take the cursor now
and just reinforce
the feedback and the feed forward part
of this because the authors spent a bit
i don't want it sort of
unpacked like they have at the at the
figure three unpacking that we have in
the bottom of the slide can you just run
the cursor over all the examples of
feedback and feed forward
going on concurrently because i think
that's that's
really important to see
that it's happening in both directions
at once
let's label
everything
and then definitely can do that
perfect thank you
okay so
light blue
is action
these are subtracted so red circles
represent expected
values
of x
the red circles
are used to make predictions about y
these are subtracted to form a
prediction error
because those lines with the arrows on
the end of them are just dependencies
they don't really show
both the feedback and the feed forward
yes agreed like having some
rounded
edges and other
um directed edges
let's see whether it's
whether they're like kind or not
um
let's start with action
action
influences the state of the world
which
an edge can be drawn
to how that changes the state of the
thermoreceptor
i thought why here was the observation
yeah
that's the state of the thermoreceptor
is the observation okay yeah so action
changes the observation the state of the
thermoreceptor
um
which is
being contrasted
with the belief about temperature
yes from there
a prediction error
is generated
it could be zero if there's no
difference or it could be higher
that can you can you just show with a
green
some colored line that has an arrow on
each end
a connection that demonstrates within
that diagram the feedback and the feed
forward at once
is that possible using this diagram
let's see it's this representation so a
single arrow that a single line that has
an arrow at both ends is a different
color so we've superimposed it over this
but that it shows that there's a
feedback feed forward loop going off
at the same time
okay so here's the temperature
information measurement flowing in to
contrast with the beliefs
and this is it is in general really
important to label the edges not just
use color
coding we'll let it roll for now the
information's flowing from the
measurement
to the belief
and then that
gives us
the prediction error
is used
in the selection of action
which then influences
future observations
now the red circles represent expected
values of x
i'm actually not sure what exactly the
red
bottom larger circle is meaning
because the prediction error
well there has to be some way of
representing that discrepancy right
so they needed they needed the second
ball on the bottom to show difference
like between prediction error and
expectation i think that's all that's
trying to show
yeah or another
possibility might be that the prior
is staying fixed
that's actually music
yeah priors can also
they can be
flexible but in this case it's a fixed
prior
that's because we're talking about
homeostasis
then
the observations
are diverging from
the prior
and the posterior
is kind of like the realized perception
which is a compromise between the
sensory data coming in
and the prior
and so yes there's a lot of degrees of
freedom depending on how parameters are
weighted this green line might
approximate the red a lot more sharply
we'd call that a weaker prior because
sensory data updates the posterior to be
more like it
or
it could be the case that
having a lot of observations different
from your prior don't change it that's a
strong prior where sensory data do not
change it as much but then here
is the prediction error
in
relationship to
x i i don't know we can look at the
paper but is mu
shown in an equation i don't have it
copied out if it is
let me look here while you're doing that
yeah
but that is the
perhaps here okay
um stephen anything
yeah i'm just noting how
the effectively the belief on
temperature
it's it flows through
the thermosector
down into the
to get the expectation and prediction
error so it's
you know it's it's it's like you've
shown there there is a
a
dynamic going down from
the belief through to prediction error
being mediated it's like the
thermoceptor is kind of like a mediator
between belief
and
[Music]
prediction error on what to do for
action
and another point i
the reason why you can't find the mu is
because it's not actually
pointed to in the description
yeah and i remember reading and looking
at looking and looking and not being
able to find it and then looping back up
up paper
to go okay so
how about feedback feed forward
now there are cases where vue is used to
describe internal states
that may be implicitly how it's being
used but it's super important that all
variables are defined in a paper i wish
they all had a table for every single
variable and expression that were used
yeah it would make the dot zeros easier
but also it would reduce uncertainty
um
for example is um
is this epsilon even described okay
steven
i mean i suppose in a thermostat in some
ways the
the internal states um
of the bioelectric strip
and in some ways it's kind of um
it holds the kind of
the the way that
um
the expectations of action can happen
because in some ways it dictates the way
that
um
the thermostat will behave
it's uh in some sort of ways even if
it's kind of a
an
analog uh process so i'm i'm thinking
like where where would the kind of in a
thermostat where would um i know this is
a homeostat so it's a bit more
sophisticated now but extrapolating that
out you've you've kind of got a belief
and
there's a belief of what something is
and then there's an expectation of what
you can do about it
um for instance i my beliefs can go
bigger than what i can do in my actions
i could have beliefs about
temperature which exceeds where
i could even exist or where i am able to
change it you know it depends on the
scenario so
there's it's sort of held in in both
scenarios in in both the body
and the context and the kind of
the the the probabilities available
okay so for a
non-living thermostat
it doesn't have a cognitive belief on
temperature but there could be something
that's computationally like that
reflected by like just a digital prior
on temperature
and again these aren't cognitive
personal affective experienced beliefs
bayesian belief this is just saying
random variable reflecting
in a model variable on temperature so
even a sincerely held incorrect
psychological belief
is not the bayesian belief they might
coincide at times if it were a parameter
but um
the belief here being
uh
the prior
it must be adaptive that's the
evolutionary twist that actually helps
resolve a lot of this because otherwise
right the design space of all edges by
all nodes
and then any variable i mean it's just
like saying
here's all the words in the dictionary
and so evolution helps restrict the
discussion
to
cases that actually do manage to achieve
adaptive control dean
and this is where that translation from
the silhouette of the head
to a statistical density
is assumed that we're the the person
who's following along with this just
sees that but it's but you can also see
how easy it is to slip
into the idea that
oh wait a second we've gone from the
physical space and we just held onto the
physical space when really now we're
talking about a statistical density
space
and again if you're not if you're not
really really careful you can see how
people can carry forward something but
the actual thing that they're talking
about has changed
that's why the word discrepancy was such
a big deal to me because i normally
gloss over things but this time it
actually
i went oh okay so there's going to be
some there's going to be some moments
here where we're actually talking about
different things even though in the
continuum
we we kind of think that they're talking
about the same thing no we're not
yep it's um
the travails of realism and
instrumentalism for biological active
inference
episode 55
because
are these terms are they an example
or is this
an example of a model being used to
discuss
a real system but
this suffice to say is the architecture
of the homeostat
it undertakes action
to reduce discrepancy
relative to a prior held belief fixed in
this case
about what temperatures are
expected slash preferred
the dialectic of the first two p's from
live stream number 37.
this is
an expectation
and a preference
because expectations having to do with
survival
are as good as preferences for survival
over evolutionary time
okay
this is going to be contrasted with
figure
3 b
which is the allostat
and so we see the same
stack
of x 1 y 1 light blue dark blue red
except there's now a second column next
to it and there's some cross
connectivity so again the x's are going
to be beliefs about so priors on
and then these are
observations and so they're saying
this generative model extends the
homeostat by including a second set of
exteroceptive variables that correspond
to light intensity
y2
observations of light
and beliefs about sunrise so like
beliefs about the generative process
so generative model of the generative
process
furthermore the model includes a
predictive relationship between sunrise
x2
and body temperature y
so
again i wish we could label every edge
because
the edges are meaning different things
even at different times
like
this is a predictive relationship
so it's an anticipatory one
but then the one about light intensity
and the belief about sunrise there would
be ways to make that an anticipatory or
an anticip or an instantaneous
relationship
but the result of this sketched
architecture
is that inferring a sunrise
which will only happen with high
posterior confidence if the visual
observations are consistent so low
prediction error
inferring a sunrise not
quote seeing a sunrise
that is not
what is happening in the model inferring
a sunrise and finding that visual
observations are compatible with it
can trigger the autonomic response the
behavior you
of thermoregulation in an anticipatory
manner that is before sunlight actually
increases body temperature well how
would the parameter be set that way
because if that were adaptive
then other parameter combinations have
been weeded out already by evolution
so that is where we tuck the thread back
into the ball of yarn which is the
parameter combinations that are
non-adaptive die
they dissipate they fail to exist
they're not going to be measured as
things in the future empirically
however you want to take it so like the
quote like how does it work
it's the same as it was 50 years ago
which is it has to do with survival of
the persistent stephen
and these um
these graphs what they're used for as
well is they they do show
beliefs tied to
the observation space that the space
available
um around the observation
uh
the you know whatever the sensorium
that is available
that's what gives the beliefs its scope
and then
the
expectations
are
tied in here more clearly to action
so the errors the errors of the the
the the
what's important the the the actual
um
dynamic that's driving action to change
something is is is coming out of the
prediction area error that's feeding
into action i think that's quite
important as because
you know this is like the proto
animal you know this is like the proto
kind of
piece here that ties into
a lot of how
we think about knowledge and meaning and
i'm not saying that i'm just i'm just
extrapolating a lot but i think it does
show how
beliefs are tied to
the type of sensorim
that is being used to shape the
observation space i think that's quite
useful
yeah and these are just yeah dean first
got
i just want to get your gut both you
guys opinions about that orange barbell
at the bottom of the diagram because
talking identity
but we're also still talking about
dependency we're talking about
duplication
we're talking about anticipation so
that's a lot of stuff packed in one
orange barbell what do you think
yeah i'm going back to the full
caption
the red circles represent the expected
values of x
so if we're interpreting these as the
posteriors on x because the expectations
the priors are the top blue ones
so
it wouldn't have to be the red circles
and they don't mention the word orange
no
it's there and it's identity
note the lateral modulatory connections
in the allostatic network c24 for
details and 24 is
the graphical brain with first and par
and device
um
so yeah again this is just a sketch
model they're not using it to fit any
data
or even simulate any data
and it does relate to what stephen said
about the
the inter sensory or the intermodal
inference which is one could imagine a
cognitive model where if sunrise
if there's noises that are associated
with sunrise
then beliefs about sunrise
can be a variable with edges coming from
different sensory modalities
so it gives us a separation of
the um organs of sense
and internal cognitive modeling stephen
yeah it gives a gives a sense of when
would something be important to act upon
so there's many many things that i could
believe i'm seeing or being perceived in
terms of this is
sunrise or this is
um
you know
this is the type of light coming in this
is the nature of the light this is where
the the light's coming from there's all
sorts of stuff the stuff that's really
filtering down
is what is
important
and this is where the affordance is
coming what affords me to make some
action
you know if it was expanding out so
there can be lots of things i noticed
like i might notice that
that there's a line there and i may
notice and believe it's orange but i may
not act upon it until i take my
attention to it and think it's useful as
there's many things going on on the page
you know so when we're
we have beliefs but then there's what's
being acted upon out of all of that
to then create
some sort of change so i think that
is also quite useful in this
architecture
cool
i want to can i add to this because i
think it's really important
um so we're talking about in the in the
context of a
of a sun coming up
but
let's let's see whether it still is true
and i think it is just to prove a point
whether that orange orange barbell
still makes sense if we're talking about
daniel anticipating 61 year old daniel
and stephen anticipating 61 year old
stephen and dean anticipating 61 year
old dean
now i'm much closer to 61 than the two
of you but do i need the mark do i need
the monte carlo do i need the play out
to be able to make that anticipation as
long as i have the identity and the
parallelism and the backwards and
forwards looking dependency that we see
between x1 and x2 and y1 and y2
that's what i think is makes this a very
interesting
way of being able to sort of build on
the previous homeostatic
example
thanks steven
yeah i think also this
speaks to traditionally
we think about the meaning what does
this mean what's all the meaning out
there as you mentioned all the data the
stuff that it could mean to relate all
these variables but ultimately
um
and the bit that is actually what
active inference gives us is that
barbell is where the meaning comes in
it's like the way to know
how
being 61 is for you dean is for you
to imagine
what it would be like
to make choices and to act in the world
as a 61 year old dean not necessarily to
go out and look at all the
the data so to speak all the beliefs and
the things we think about the world but
to actually bring that in and
and of course you've got a better chance
to do that because you're closer to
being
that kind of dean
um so i think that's quite interesting
that barbell at the bottom in terms of
um
pairing together
the kind of beliefs about what actions
and prediction areas are available
and it's more into that meaningful
action meaningfulness
realm rather than what does it mean
what's the data tell us so
yeah
we might we might get there and i'm not
pushing back on what you're saying
stephen we might get there but i think
for now
what we're saying what we're saying is
is that in order to get there we have to
have more than
more than a
a single
stack
of dependencies
we have to have
a double stack
in order to be able to
extend the homeostatic
nature
of how we've evolved to where we are
i don't know again i'm not pushing back
on you i'm just saying i don't want to
jump that i don't want to jump that
firing pistol just yet because i think
that orange barbell is going to turn
into a green arrow and then all hail is
going to break loose anyway so
we should carry on i don't want to take
steven's stuff away
but i want i think i want to park it
because we're going to go somewhere in a
minute
i'm hesitant to ascribe too much specif
specificity to something that wasn't
labeled in the caption doesn't have a
clear labeling in the figure either but
i think it
is already demonstrated that
using graphical frameworks and
partitionings like we have an active
inference we can start to approach some
of these questions like how would
different kinds of variables be
connected how does that relate to future
inference on action counterfactuals etc
okay so
these sections
um four five six seven
were just laying out the relationship
between
an evolutionary or physiological
function
like homeostasis allostasis or simple
behavioral control models of things that
are core evolutionary features and
functions
connecting them
to the kinds of graphical
representations
which are like a little bit of a hybrid
of a bayesian graph
and
a factor graph
because there's some kind of
computations being implied here
whereas in a bayesian graph the edges
only reflect statistical dependencies
whereas we're bringing in a little bit
more of like a nuanced type relationship
that one could imagine
could be unpacked a bit more
were to be specified but it's just to
show
how
different
graphical models
relate to
different functions
architectural
underpinnings
whether you think this is the actual
architecture
or
whether it's just an instrumental
architecture like a model structure on a
given phenomena
how do model architectures relate to
evolutionary functions
where is
evolutionary time in this model we
started out by asking like how do
cognitive phenotypes arise
specifically over evolutionary but also
over developmental time
and that's where we get to one of the
main
pieces and contributions of the paper
which is
figure four
the five main dimensions of elaboration
of generative models introduced in this
paper
so
there's other kinds of
changes and ways that this structure
could evolve but they're going to focus
on these five
there's starting with the homeostat
does that have to be our starting point
maybe not
but starting with the homeostat
there's the i
operation which is identity unchanged
there's i plus i which is just a
parallel isolated duplication
that's like from one photoreceptor to
going to two photoreceptors so to speak
there's the allostat
which is a duplication as well as a
cross linking
so these are just
sketches one could also probably write
that one as like
a duplication followed by a linking and
there's no like change in linking for
example here so this is like
a few of a taxonomy of operations
there's
increases in temporal depth within a
level of the hierarchy so looking
one more unit further in time
at a given time scale
and then there's hierarchical nesting
with an h
and the figure is shown like this
because these are like the things that
can happen to the homeostat
and then
they can have a second round and so on
and so on
there's so many other ones that could
happen like where is
reduction where's loss
where's deduplication where's the
uncoupling of the allostat reduction of
temporal depth reduction of hierarchy so
there's a broad space
but one of the main contributions of
this paper
is to connect
functionally oriented graphical models
of homeostatic and physiological
function to
the operations
that result in the elaboration of
simpler model architectures
into
different architectures steen
this is an interesting part i know
steven wants to have to say something
too but really quickly there's no plus
minus multiply and divide
there's an operation but there there's
no
symbolism for that and again
that's that keeps it safe on a
statistical level
i think that's that's a that's a nice
tell there i want to again for somebody
who's just sort of looking at this for
the first time pointing that out it's
not there and because it's not present
that tells us something to your point
about maybe how do we get
d duplication
yes it's um
well i plus i it is like
it's it's a
suggestive use of the addition operator
but we're not adding these just like
integers so yes
they're kind of like categorical
operations
that constitute this evolutionary
algebra
okay stephen anything on figure four
yeah i was just saying that
i was saying they've set up they've set
a
a kind of a paradigm from the homeostat
and they've taken that through and
they've shown that plausibly can
carry through to cognition
and then like you say there can be other
ways but what they've now given is
they've given
some legs another way to think of the
legs that can be attached to that
paradigm because this modeling approach
while they could have chosen a lot
others by taking it
there are certain things that your heart
baked into that early stage
choice making which then
makes other paradigms wouldn't fit with
it right you know you certain certain
even when you go instrumental or realist
you know your instrumental models your
realist models don't make sense unless
you
with this unless you take in some of the
paradigms that this structuring
creates
yeah
agreed thanks so just maybe think like
is this
functional model realism
like the function of the model
is what is being tracked
through time
and so that
there's many other
alterations that could occur and then
there's
the even more granular like parametric
changes or changes in connectivity or
edge types
and then i think
uh
as you said dean when all hell breaks
loose
what's interesting here let's look at
the allostat
in a little bit closer detail
okay so previously we looked at the
allostat and we were like
okay there's an orange bar
now
the allostat
has a green bar
it's a green arrow and it's a
unidirectional one well this one
independence
the allostat
has the green bar oh it's okay well
those are my bad eyes because i saw i
saw the little arrow from the blue
actually turning i didn't actually see
that there was two circles thank you
there's my 60 year old eyes for you yeah
um
okay
cool um
and so
each of these are in quite a different
domain
um or at least like a different
aspect of cognition
and these are the transitions that it
can engage in
so like
duplication retains the exact same
function but it's a very important step
and that's a little bit what i explored
in the dot zero with genetic
duplications like on the left side here
at the screen
having a
region of the genome duplicate
yes one of the duplicate copies can just
degenerate
that may be like opening up space or
creating motifs for other kinds of later
evolutionary steps so even this is not
like a failure it's just a change
there's neo-functionalization
where then those two models can start to
sub-specify like if you only have one
photoreceptor it has to be doing what
it's doing but duplicating it
then allows one to focus on a different
wavelength than the other for example
and then there's um sub
functionalization which is where
initially a composite function a b
becomes
two like enzymes start to sub-specialize
on one of the two functions of the
ancestral so this is kind of like a role
duplication
um okay so duplication is an important
event
then there's the allostat and
multiple things happen with a
but we're seeing it as there is a
duplication occurring and there's also
cross-linking occurring
between beliefs in one modality or
beliefs about one type of thing
influencing observations
um or in about another kind of thing
as well as this lateral modulatory
uh green
orange bar
um
we have and then we have two kinds of
expansions into temporal depth
a sort of local expansion
with the t operation
just pushing the model one step deeper
and then the h hierarchical nesting
operation
which brings it to another time scale of
analysis dean
and this is where i really struggled and
that is in when they were at allostat
it wasn't just comparative i felt like
you had to build in time
especially if you were talking about
identity
but then it was like no we're just going
to leave it comparative and then we're
going to introduce the oneness of this i
mean i understand why they're doing that
to try to make it tractable
but i don't know how they can
say it can be comparative
meaning
i know the difference between a and b
right now
but not not sort of address the fact
that
in order to differentiate into a and b
some some amount of time
had to
had to have been applied to that split
so i had i was i was saying you have to
go back in time in order to just be able
to do a comparison
so it's temporal only going forward in
time i don't mean all hell broke loose
but i mean i i did ask this question
you're right like here there's um
there's the triggering in an
anticipatory manner
and so in one view it's like but this is
a single time step model
so how could that occur
because it doesn't have a temporal depth
on the other hand
again like kind of that those two senses
of representation in the structural
sense if the model's a single time step
model it can't have a representation
through deep time ergo it cannot be
anticipatory functionally
right the other side of the coin
would be
if it's enough at this time step
such that beliefs about sunrise trigger
and a response
the model can be functionally
anticipatory
without a temporal depth representation
right which is why the representation
discussion was very important leading up
to this one
because
we're all over those eight quadrants
here because
in evolution and this is something that
like cognitive psych people talk about
and is like
are cognition being shaped towards
effective which is to say productive
slash reproductive
success
not towards like ultimate truth
discovery
and so
should we be too surprised that our
instrumentation
which has had a certain objective
function
is then susceptible to
being convinced about things that
are not
true
well i don't i don't socialize with
those people so i i don't know i just
knew that when i was looking at it i was
thinking in real practical terms
what what what is built into this in
order for it to still make sense and
that wasn't necessarily parsed out
in the diagram you kind of had to fill
that in
through your own interpretation of what
was going on so thus back to discrepancy
that discrepancy thing is going to come
up again and again and i'm really glad
that they inserted it at the beginning
steven
i think it's useful here to hear this
temple depth and hierarchical
depth
being sort of
spelt out so
because
i think it sometimes it's a little
confusing in other papers quite where it
fits
so temporal depth and this again might
be where some of this ontology work can
be useful just to see if that can be
kind of consistent but if temporal depth
is you know you've got
variables for past present and future
states
but they're operating
maybe
maybe within the same kind of dynamics
and then if you've got
different um
temple
rates
operating simultaneously
then you get that hierarchical depth
and i thought in the past i'd sometimes
thought temporal depth would have
covered that more hierarchical
depth
so
you know this is interesting to think
about whether this might be
actually the way that that
differentiation is best made
differentiation is probably best made
with reference to a specific model and
this gives us the design language
and the grammar and the motifs
so if we want to predict 100 years in
the future
should we have
a decade
model
with 10 year models
that's a times depth of 10 decades
and then a nested model with a depth of
10 years
or
but we have a one layer model
with a hundred
they're very different
and it's not to say that one is like
more accurate or less and depending on
how the exact situation is set up maybe
the computational requirements of one or
higher are different than the other
but
that's the discussion to have do we want
to have a b
transition matrix
let's look at a nested model with
temporal depth
so here
we have on the top level of the model
s state 2
this is
temporal depth
happening at the upper level of the
model three discrete time points in an
upper level
that is temporal depth
there's also nesting
within each
um
time step
there's a cognitive rollout on three
time steps this is one type of nested
model but there's other nestings that
can exist
so here we see
a depth of two
and then at each
level
of the nesting there's three
temporal depth
but they're totally different in
architecture and in function so it is
the interesting discussion like
especially when we have to do
multi-scale prediction like fermi
estimation
so if the prediction is within one time
scale
there isn't necessarily a need to nest
but
once we get into larger time scales or
where there's recurrence over multiple
time scales
it makes sense to have a nesting model
like if we wanted to predict someone's
activity over the next seven days
it might make sense to have a day
model with a nested model inside of that
because then within each day there could
be parameter setting
versus just trying to fit one time
series and find the parameters
that make that one time series oscillate
in a circadian way
instead we just need a day model with a
very specific kind of simple transition
and then a transition at a nested level
with a depth that's measured at the
hourly or the minute time scale rather
than the days
and that becomes especially important
when doing
family based model fitting like
variational inference
so we're not just like getting all the
data points and fitting a spline through
them
but we actually
need to have appropriate model structure
otherwise free energy minimization
will drive right off the cliff
just like we talked about with axel's
bacterium
so if we want to do free energy
minimization and model selection
on
model structures
we can find the best model relatively
easily given the families that we've
specified but there's no guarantees once
we step outside of that spotlight
that we're even in the right category
structurally and so that's why
humans
having these design motifs in mind and
many many many more
helps us not get into what seems to be a
global optimization
based upon free energy minimization but
actually is a very relatively local
optimization based upon unimaginative
model structured learning stephen
yeah thanks that's really helpful and
and it also ties into something i've
been really thinking about in terms of
the modeling itself is
these these these scales these steps you
know you're talking about the multi-year
decades
when we're modeling it's like what do we
have access to
so we tend to ascribe that in terms of
what can we externalize what can we use
to
put something into a model if it's
instrumental and then of course there's
a question of well what is the realist
perspective on that and what is there
that's within
our conscious awareness of being in the
world something that can be reported as
an event a story
and
what time scales are present there when
you get into 100 years it's beyond that
so then you're saying okay what are you
going to extrapolate what sort of
temple structure but on the other scale
if i'm asking what do i think
i expect you to do next or to dean to do
next
and that might seem intuitive i can have
a whole series of
temple and nested scales going on which
is not even available to me
in a in a cognitive conscious way
i might have a sense i have a feel for
what i think is going on but a lot of my
um predictive processing
will be happening at rates
unavailable to my conscious awareness
so that's that also ties in i suppose
i'm not saying it's an art sort of adds
to the challenge i suppose but it is the
challenge of
you know how much ends up being what we
can get a measure on to put into our
model
as much as what it is and that's the
same challenge in a way that comes even
from the realist perspective at some
level as an organism what is it that i
even can access
in some realistic way not saying we can
model it or no
that could be put into something like
this sorry you're going to say something
well all i was going to add is that i
mean so the paper's talking about how do
we how do we use
certain math
to be able to understand maybe the
evolution of of cognition
right that's essentially what the paper
is trying to give you know point us in
that direction so
again in order to make this accessible
in order to sort of lower the barrier
for people who actually want to have
this make sense because they don't
necessarily spend
sums and sums of hours on on trying to
figure this stuff out like the authors
or maybe even us
i'm going to i want to point out
something that i think is obvious to us
but maybe not so obvious to people who
are looking at this and going
i have no idea what they're saying
i think first of all is that there's a
chrono a chronolog chronology which we
keep going back to not just at the
temporal depth level
but so that's relativity math there's an
evolutionary aspect to this so that's
algebraic math and there's a dependency
so there's a statistical math
do we have to be poly math in order to
be able to feel our way through this
and i'm going to go back to what i said
at the end of the 37
first carl firsten said you're not gonna
be a polymath but you better be
at least somewhat comfortable feeling
comfortable
with the math because there's no one
math
that's going to get you here it's a
blending of all of them
and then it's how it how you feel about
that
that's probably going to be the thing
that lowers
the the impediment to really being able
to use this now in real practical terms
going forward so what's the next
evolutionary step right it's how you're
able to turn this into something
so i think that's
i think that's one of the great gifts of
this paper if
you're not afraid of being
if you don't consider if you don't want
to identify now where you don't
duplicate now
or you don't allostat now as a polymath
maybe maybe that's something
we
we owe people
that want to get into this
maybe the british
pronunciation of maths
helps
reflect that there's already a plurality
of maths
and kirby erner coming more from the
synergetic side talks a lot about this
actually like how
the discourse around math as universal
language
makes it sound like math is a singular
when actually math is a pluriverse and
so maths reflects that a little better
better
it's not like
these are um
just sort of
slopes on one mountain and that's mount
math and it's so high and only a few
people get to the top and scale every
side
this is just like
we're using maths
yes of all different kinds steven
and often that you see a lot of this in
the papers that are published around
active inference there's often a team of
people a group of people where maybe one
member has that
higher level
understanding the math but the other
question is is to understand
what would it mean to make an
observation now that could be a very the
mathematician may not be the one what
like some of the work with ryan smith's
work on the gut
you know it was like well
they're going to do gut inference well
how do you get
some tractable
source
on what's the gut doing so they created
some electrode i'm not quite sure how
they did it but they had some way of
getting
sensory information effectively sensory
information or effectively some sort of
information to put into their model
and
so knowing how
action
and observations
can flow in and the implications of that
i think is also kind of a
a big part of
of this right and
in some cases it may be
the trivial part because it's fairly
obvious in other parts that may be the
biggest
barrier
to and then that may be the biggest
barrier as well often in in organisms
right how do you how do you even access
plausibly
the approximation science which isn't so
approximate approximate it's just chaos
that is tractable
yeah the rate limiting step
or
impact and improvement
in the real world
is unlikely to be any single
individual's
conceptualization of math
on a team
if it's structured appropriately
and
for those pushing the frontiers of math
their understanding of math is quite
literally
a rate limiting step for them
or maybe it might be something very
mundane like
time availability but when it comes to
thinking about
real model based science and
translational applications of active
inference
i think that we're working towards new
ways of
combining skills
and having shared knowledge resources
that help make that make sense
and using
shared language and
ontologies narratives formal documents
tools on ft
because we're doing it on teams and
we're online
let's just in the last
20 30 minutes
go through the final pieces of the paper
so that this dot one will have been like
a first sweep
initial pheromone deposition and then we
can return and take some cul-de-sacs etc
so
section nine
explores a little bit how the
duplication
operation
allows for multiple behaviors to arise
and that's sort of by analogy to the um
the genomic duplications and
specializations and all those different
routes that can occur
here they connected duplication
a little bit more directly
to the factor graph models
in the sense that duplicated
motifs have dynamics that are conserved
over different sensory motor domains
so let's just say that we just had a
visual model with the column of visual
and then we duplicated it so now we have
two photoreceptors with parallel columns
and now
the photoreceptor in the second one
changes into a chemoreceptor because
instead of expressing rhodopsin protein
it's expressing an olfactory receptor
protein
there can be a conservation of the
dynamics
of inference
even when the observation has changed
but it was a slot for observation
and so we went from having like
monocular vision
to binocular vision
to
monocular vision and
olfactory perception but you can't get
there in one jump to just like duplicate
and transpose
it's not likely to happen in an
evolutionary context
and
we can see the structure
of these graphical models
as equivalent to being factorized
probability distributions
which is to say that the sparse
connectivity of variables
means that we can make parts of the
model
that can be like fine-tuned
independently in a way that can be fit
very attractively
that's the factor graph that's
factorized bayesian inference and we've
talked about that in other places but
just to here all we need to say is
duplication
enables
like a control c
control v copy paste and then let's edit
the other version
but that can now happen with
evolutionary features and functions dean
real quick your hand gestures in this
section point to the orthogonal
orthogonal mesh beginning
okay and then point two i'd like to pull
that apart a little bit but let's carry
on but that's that's what i've took away
from this the men the mesh began
and in the beginning there was a mesh
begins
we'll return to that for um
dot two
yeah okay
section 10
talks about
temporal depth it's about time
and about the endowing of generative
models with temporal depth and the way
that that supports prospective inference
anticipation
or retrospective inference
which is like memory
so here's what the operator looks like
we have x sub tau
x at a time point and then now there's x
tau plus one the next time point
or t plus one
could be now and then t
could be
the last moment
so
um
memory
i still see figure four
um
slide 29
okay
yeah so the structure of anticipation
and of memory are very similar it just
depends whether one has the um
stream of observations happening
on the left side
and a prospection or the stream of
observations are on the right side and
in which case it's retrospection stephen
yeah i mean sort of ties in they talk
about what the police do it's very hard
for someone to lie backwards so you
always get them to tell their story
backwards because it's a it's very hard
for them to to do that because
you say if we're
creating things
retrospectively but
playing them forward so to speak it
would kind of time without
i want to emancipate that
i looked up police in the paper i see
policies
is that policies
um
it's a great opportunity for my favorite
joke but i won't
um
this section talks about temporal depth
okay
from whence temporal depth
various researchers have speculated that
a major driving force for the
development of deep temporal models was
foraging
and there's a lot of interesting
empirical and conceptual reasons to
think about
foraging in terms of temporal and
spatial depth of model
and that's true in the vertebrates
where they're
discussing mainly like hippocampus and
entorinal system
and in the invertebrates that don't have
a hippocampus enterorinal system but
it's one reason why comparative
neuroscience is so important
because it prevents us from getting
fixed on specific anatomical
realizations
of given functional attributes of
evolutionary systems like
if the story of memory is just about
some brain region in humans
it may be a useful model it's not even
to say that it's inaccurate it's not
even to say that it's a partial model it
just is a model of that whereas if we
want to understand
a given cognitive function in a broader
context
we have to pull back somewhere a little
bit
beyond or
in complement to the anatomy because we
need the empirical anatomy
to have anything specific to be talking
about
but
it isn't just the case that vertebrae
anatomy is the way to do active
inference uh stephen
yeah i think this is really helpful
because
it it shows that you know the traps you
were just mentioning there that people
we fall into is like
humans have you know the the frontal
cortex it's all about this new then
what's the new parts of the brain that
are there but we don't say that with a
formula one car we say well it's just
got a primitive engine thing in there
and the rest of it's evolved it's like
well that's itself different like this
and the same with the mark someone's
conversation you know
the the the evolution of the break
what's often dismissed as the primitive
parts of the brain
they they themselves can have been
more sophisticated although they're
doing more things but that they
they they they may be helped to be doing
more
than they were as opposed to there's
something else um
that is doing all the heavy lifting
which i think is certainly common
a common misconception i think in
psychology anyway
dean
can i read quickly from the paper sure
okay the evolution of temporally deep
models from simpler models could been
realized during evolution via the
progressive keyword here partialization
of an initially undifferentiated model
so a relative sense of an invariance
i.e a model that does not distinguish
present from past future
into a model that features separate
latent states for the past present and
future
this is the part i loved a key drive for
this factorization
or parcelation parcellation may have
been the observation and progressive
internalization of the sensory motor
sequences sequence sequentially
that the animal creates and experiences
while acting
while acting in other words the
self-modeling of one's own sequential
behavior patterns c53 for a
computational example i didn't open up
53 but again if we want to talk about
the polymath piece of this and the fact
that our hex cells
have to do some partialization it's
right there
in terms of sort of the the
the next layer
on top of this as we move up through
that evolutionary cycle
yeah 53 is
stoin of
at all the hippocampal formation as a
hierarchical generative model supporting
generative replay and continual learning
there's a ton
that could be said about that from like
a computational and a neuro anatomical
perspective
the internalization of the sensory motor
sequences
relates to the sensory motor detachment
that we talked about in the
representation paper
so if um some motor region in the brain
if it's like a marionette and the
fingers and then the motor um plant
so that motor region is
has to be coupled to the activity of
that motor region like either in a one
directional way or maybe even in a
bi-directional way let's just say so
that system
like
as it thinks so it does
and vice versa
it cannot engage in counter factuals
because any
direction that the neural system turns
the motor system is just simply doing
that
so it is not able to engage over
evolutionary time in bowel adaptive
action
the ones that do no longer persist
it's just it's always what ties it back
to reality into like the finite amount
of entities on the finite spaceship
earth like darwin's famous calculation
like if the number of elephants slowly
reproducing like they'll cover the earth
unless
their population levels are kept in
check
and so
um once there's sensory motor detachment
so there's some brain region either a
motor region or some supplemental area
some ancillary area
that's able to intervene in that process
or somehow play a role that's detached
from the motor activity
now there can be like a motor planning
occurring
that opens up the affordance of temporal
depth or of counter factuals all these
other cognitive functions
arising
via the sensory motor detachment
and so
um
foraging is an awesome place to look at
that
for a lot of reasons
in different
life forms and computational forging and
so like just a few of the notes were
like
what are the real cognitive demands of
foraging
for different creatures and
what about internal foraging like mental
foraging
and these papers are very good
foraging in mind and foraging in
semantic fields
both very
useful
because they have to do with the way
that um
they have some nice maths too but they
have to do with
how
actions that are spatial
can have conserved dynamics structurally
just like we explored here
to mental actions and then we see them
come together like with a memory palace
or something like that
um
so foraging is cool it's good to study
eleven endowing generative models with
hierarchical depth of four's multi-scale
inference we kind of addressed that
earlier with like the decades and years
nested temporal modeling is not the same
as just deep temporal modeling
and then um and another way to look at
that is like how many operations you
would need to get to a hundred years
well if you're gonna do only temporal
depth it's gonna take plus a hundred or
ninety nine time steps versus if it's
one nesting and then 10 on the higher
order than 10 on the lower order it was
21 operations
and so then
there's shorter
sequence of events to achieve a higher
performance model assuming that they're
appropriate
um
section 12
uh yeah go ahead
just one thing just on on that modeling
it's also interesting think about how we
think of time because like indigenous
approaches tends to be well as a
cyclical time right so
things in the future will be a repeat of
the cycle
so
the times of uh i thought of in in the
cyclic motion of the sort of passing of
the day passing of the
um and of course we have this
we we have this assumption of time
stretching out you know
so is it that we will uh you know over
time is it
well what will things be like in four
generations
and
um and if my world or my ecology
follows certain cyclical patterns and
it's very stable maybe that's quite a
good way to think about
um you know it's like say plant plant
the tree now to help the people in 150
years you know
so um
it sort of comes back to
there's different ways to construct
how we
think about time
[Music]
cool
so 12 looks into
phylogenetic tree of the evolution of
generative model so
what is a phylogenetic tree
and what's the relationship between
active inference slash fep and evolution
well
we'll have more to share
in the coming papers as always but how
do they address it specifically here in
figure five
they um map on will root the tree so
technically as shown right here it's an
unrooted tree there is an implicit
rooting here
but it's a very interesting feature of
phylogenetics that few outside of the
field know about that computationally
the tree is often inferred in an
unrooted fashion like by
clustering the ones that are close and
finding the relationships etc
however
that is leaving an ambiguity
as to where the root of the tree is so
like for example if this is the overall
connectivity of the um
based upon the phylogenetic inference
this is what the tree topology has been
inferred to look like
and somebody might say well it looks
like this one the red one and then the
green one below it
they are um
they're clearly very closely related
but actually if the root
comes in here
then
that's not necessarily the case
so the rooting of a phylogenetic tree is
very important and a tree that's rooted
inappropriately or has an inappropriate
out group selection
is just
it's worse than illegible because it's
highly legible and it can have a high
statistical confidence but it can have
an absolutely non-biological topology
but assuming that they meant the tree to
be rooted here
here the branches
are where there's going to be different
operators occurring including the i
identity unchanging one
and then
the edges
reflect like bifurcations expeciation
events
so here there's an ancestral homeostat
and then the lineage leading to orange
did not go
undergo any changes that were
non-conservative
on the branch leading to these sister
species
there was a duplication
and then it stayed the same and stayed
the same and then the purple node is
going to have
two duplicated homeostats and so they're
just overlying
evolutionary algebra the steps that they
gave
on to the topology of speciation and so
that
um as they discuss
opens up a way to think from this sort
of graphical functional perspective
which is compatible with active
to think about how for example
from the species today
we could infer some of the schema of the
early vertebrate brain or the early
prime vein
or push it back further what about the
common ancestors of the vertebrates and
the invertebrates
and all these other questions but that's
kind of what they lay out here
and so these are familiar models to
evolutionary biologists
like
uh phylogenetic
ancestral state reconstructions of
phenotype
which are often even done in a bayesian
way
like there's an algorithm beast
bayesian
estimation of ancestral states
this is also a bayesian
model that allows us to do
reconstruction of ancestral states but
it's in a very very different way
than it's been approached outside of the
active world
but that's figure 5
and
that's where we see the evolutionary
algebra the design patterns or the
pattern language
for
structural changes in generative model
superimposed on
species relatedness and a phylogenetic
tree
any thoughts on five
i tried to convert this and reapply it
to my
picking of teams in the march madness
table and i wasn't able to take
philosophic
trees and and convert them into winning
thousands of dollars on betting on
college basketball so despite my best
efforts
it's it's kind of contained and for what
what it represents
i mean not to foreshadow too hard but i
think
live stream number 39 and 40
might constitute march madness
and then also here's another um you know
for those who watch
okay here now we have a little bit of a
march madness bracket going don't we
here's bracketology
that is so fantastic
so here we go
yep so now we have um now here the root
could have been here
and then here's like two big species
clades like two like this is like
vertebrates and invertebrates and then
there's some rooted clade
so that's like why it's important to
root the tree because here it looks like
all of these are sister to each other at
the exclusion of this one but then if we
were to have rooted that tree like
here
then actually this is a small sister out
group to all of these
right
and so it the rooting and the
contextualizing
is really important it's just like it's
super interesting because it seems like
you put in so much data into these
phylogenetic models and it seems like
literally how could this not converge on
a super obvious answer i mean
isn't it clear how these ants are
related to each other phylogenetically
but then there's a little bit of nuance
that enters the picture stephen
yeah it's curious that the allostatic
can
recombine with the homeostatic
to give a base level temporal
it's um
like that doesn't it doesn't deflate
back to
just staying
anaesthetic i suppose there would be
they just don't show that
it could
um you could have
if it did that i suppose you just
wouldn't talk about it
you know it's got a
the when it goes a then it goes a i
goes to ht
sorry yeah it's a th yeah so we have a
homeostat
here we have two homeostats
two homeostats and now here we have one
homeostat and one allostat in this blue
node
and so that um
but they're just kind of giving general
examples like it would have been cool to
see
um this is where we're talking about
um
mammals
and here's non-mammal vertebrates like
here is a specific brain region and also
that is
in this um
chakraborty and jarvis 2015 paper
this paper um
gets more into the nuances of
neuroanatomy and neurogenetics
and how like duplication
in
brain regions can be underpinned by
developmental neurogenetic changes
and they do link that a little bit more
closely like to studying the bird brain
and the song and motor
system in parrots
which is also cool because birdsong has
been studied with active so like there
could be a nice
building upon this
work and connecting it to some of the um
structure
fitting in figure five so it could
almost be like you've got yeah you've
got parts of the brain
which are more
allostatic orientated or homostatic
orientated and
that so in a way by
the structuring of that
gives
some sort of differentiation in terms of
how information and control will be
carried out
yeah totally and like um extending
temporal depth within a model
it's like a brain region getting a
little bigger let's just say not that
size is correlated with function in that
specific way but then duplicating brain
regions is like duplicating
laterally or nesting of brain regions
it's hierarchical
think about how the eyes developed the
insect eye
it has a relatively simple
module
but then insect eyes can change in size
over evolutionary time very radically
from like taking up you know half of the
head
to being just one photoreceptor or even
being lost
because they're existing in more of a um
duplicable motif
whereas
the binocular eye system that mammals
have
it's not as amenable to like just
doubling into four eyes
or
you know splitting into two in the
middles or something like that whereas
the insect compound eye has like some of
those evolutionary affordances
um
so then
understanding like parameter change
within a model
and then structure learning
on populations of models and what are
the mutational adjacencies
there's so many awesome areas and it's
like truly just beginning for
evolutionary bio inactive stephen
yeah it was really helpful like having
someone like yourself who's got that
background to go through that's quite
helpful because it's a
it's a little
it's a little bit intimidating actually
at first sight seeing this um for me but
i and i see the logic what you're saying
it's uh it's quite exciting actually
seeing that and again one of the things
this paper does is it's
it's tying threads together
so um which
seem very distant in in or almost
in traditional terms like
well i don't like using the word
kamikaze but it's a little bit like um
yeah it's a bit bit overwhelming often
so i think uh
it's but but of course that's the beauty
of um active is it has that unifying
potential
um so thanks
cool yeah thank you i agree like there's
some labeling
this is rarely included unless it's a
time calibrated phylogenetic tree but
like we're looking at the passage of
time
but that's not even always shown and so
um
yes dean we'll have our final thoughts
can you just go back to that because i i
really i didn't prompt you to put that
up there but i really like that because
this at some point we're going to have
to and point to talk about
that sort of basal gating part of this
and most things that are are
are
organized as if then cause allergy but
you just said it it's then if
go or don't go is very dependent on then
before
we choose to go or don't go right go or
don't go is still
held open until one of the others
decided so
another thank you for that because that
again that in the point two
we should maybe talk a little bit about
that
cool yeah there's so many ways to think
about like this garden of forking paths
branching paths
how that relates to parameter updating
bayesian belief updating and structure
learning
what about when the structure of a model
is a parameter in a nested model
so then that sort of blurs the line from
the bottom looking up it looks like
structure learning but then from the top
looking down it looks like parameter
fitting
right
and if only we had like some mathematics
to describe that
okay any
final
thoughts or what are we excited about
for the dot two next week
um well my last thought um is uh yeah
i'm excited to keep this going because i
think this has got a lot of legs to it
um
i think one thing that comes to mind as
well with all this
progressively
um increased temporal and hierarchical
depth
is is maybe where some of the more basic
uh elements still have a really useful
part to play is is what mark mike levine
said about when do we stop like so we've
got all these ways where we can start to
okay so we've got all these ways that we
can think how do we know when to stop
and to
sit down i mean it may be in the
ultimate ways between our tummy maybe
that's where the gut is so useful like
at the end of the day the brain can go
running off and maybe the gut and the
heart need to say
okay
sit down
get some food so which i might well i'm
gonna get a drink of honey now but uh
i'll bid you for well thank you for a
great dark time but i'll i'll i'll hear
your last thoughts as well
dean
uh
i hate having the last word so you won't
have it don't worry you'll have it and i
just appreciate what steven just said
because i
i think that that's a big part in this
ability to go from word
back into the phenomenological space and
i think there are other other brains
that we know of now
that play a significant role in that not
just the one that
turns everything into symbols
great
my last thought is
there's no better drink after a foraging
trip than honey
all right
thank you and talk to you later
bye